Guide to the MacLeish Family Papers, 1898-1946
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
MacLeish Family Papers
1898-1946
MacLeish Family
0.7 cubic feet (4 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence between the members of the MacLeish Family, including parents Martha and Andrew and their children Archibald, Kenneth, Norman, and Ishbel, as well as the children of Andrew's previous marriages, Bruce, Blanche and Lily.
Biographical Note
The MacLeish Family represented in this collection include Martha and Andrew and their children Archibald, Kenneth, Norman, and Ishbel, as well as the children of Andrew's previous marriages, Bruce, Blanche and Lily. Martha Hillard MacLeish (whose nickname was "Patty") was president of Rockford Seminary (now Rockford College) from 1884-1888. Andrew MacLeish was the founder and manager of the retail operations of Carson, Pirie, Scott and Company in Chicago. He was also a key figure in the founding of the modern University of Chicago. Their son, Archibald MacLeish, became a Pulitzer Prize-winning poet and the Librarian of Congress.
Chronology
1838 June Andrew MacLeish born
1856 August 17 Martha Hillard born
1858 December 25 Andrew MacLeish married Lilias Young — they had two daughters, Lily (b. 1860) and Blanche (b. 1862)
1878 September Lilias MacLeish died
1878 Martha Hillard graduated from Vassar College
1881 March Andrew MacLeish married (Martha) Louise Little — they had one son, Bruce (b. 1882)
1884-1888 Martha Hillard served as President of Rockford Seminary
1888 August 22 Andrew MacLeish married Martha Hillard
1889 July 1 Martha Louise MacLeish born (died 1890 August 6)
1890 August 29 Norman Hillard MacLeish born
1892 May 7 Archibald MacLeish born
1894 September 19 Kenneth MacLeish born (Died 1918 October 10 in WWI)
1897 March 20 Ishbel Marjoribanks MacLeish (VC 1920) born
1928 January 14 Andrew MacLeish died
1936 Martha Hillard MacLeish received honorary L.L.D. from Rockford College
1947 December 21 Martha Hillard MacLeish died
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence between the members of the MacLeish Family, including parents Martha and Andrew and their children Archibald, Kenneth, Norman, and Ishbel, as well as the children of Andrew's previous marriages, Bruce, Blanche and Lily. Of particular note are the letters between Kenneth MacLeish and his parents. Kenneth, who died when his fighter plan went down during World War I, was a favorite of Archibald MacLeish and the subject of several of his poems.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Martha Hillard MacLeish File, Alumnae/i Biographical Files
Subject Headings
Names:
MacLeish, Andrew, 1838-1928; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982--Family; MacLeish, Kenneth, 1894-1918; MacLeish, Martha Hillard, 1856-1947
VCL Categories
Family
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, June 2012.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Lochland School, October 2002 (M2002-016).
Container List
- Andrew to Blanche, 1916 Dec 20 (Folder 1.1)
- Andrew to Ishbel, 1913-1922 (Folder 1.2)
- Andrew to Kenneth, 1911-1914 (Folder 1.3)
- Andrew to Kenneth, 1915-1918 (Folder 1.4)
- Andrew to Martha, 1919-1920 (Folder 1.5)
- Andrew to Mary R. Hillard, 1915-1916 (Folder 1.6)
- Andrew to Scotland family, 1915-1919 (Folder 1.7)
- Andrew to other family, 1915, 1917 (Folder 1.8)
- Martha to Andrew, 1898-1910 (Folders 1.9-1.19)
- Martha to Andrew, 1912-1926 (Folders 2.1-2.6)
- Ada to Andrew and Martha, ca. 1919 May (Folder 2.7)
- Archibald to parents, [1914-1917], n.d. (Folder 2.8)
- Letters regarding Archibald's appendectomy, 1912 (Folder 2.9)
- Blanche to Andrew, 1898-1920, 1925, n.d. (Folder 2.10)
- Bruce to parents, 1904 Feb 24 (Folder 2.11)
- Ishbel to parents, 1915-1926, n.d. (Folder 2.12)
- Kenneth to parents, 1907-1918, n.d. (Folders 2.13-2.20)
- Lily to Andrew, 1899, 1920, n.d. (Folder 2.21)
- Norman to parents, 1906-1920, 1925 (Folder 2.22)
- Mary R. Hillard to Andrew, 1915 Nov 8 (Folder 2.23)
- John H. Wood to Andrew, 1904, 1925 (Folder 3.1)
- John E. Scott to Andrew, 1904 (Folder 3.2)
- Scotland family to Andrew, 1914-1919 (Folder 3.3)
- Miscellaneous family to Andrew, 1903-1925, n.d. (Folder 3.4)
- Ishbel to Bruce and Elizabeth, 1943, n.d. (Folder 3.5)
- Andrew to Governor Frank Lowden re Haldan Cleminson case, 1917 (Folder 3.6)
- Andrew — Letters from and relating to John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1898-1916 (Folder 3.7)
- Andrew — Church and Missionary letters, 1903-1918 (Folder 3.8)
- Miscellaneous letters to Andrew, 1905-1920 (Folder 3.9)
- Andrew — Travel documents, 1920 (Folder 3.10)
- War time addresses of Norman, Kenneth and Archibald (Folder 3.11)
- Empty envelopes (Folder 3.12)
- Children's expenses — Archibald (Folder 4.1)
- Children's expenses — Ishbel (Folder 4.2)
- Children's expenses — Kenneth (Folder 4.3)
- Children's expenses — Mixed (Folder 4.4)
- Clippings (Folder 4.5)
- Andrew — Finances and business (Folder 4.6)